Mss.Rec.3
American Philosophical Society
Onondaga material
1950
Mss.Rec.3
American Philosophical Society
22.0 Reel(s)
Recorded in 1950 with native consultants Lucenda George and Pat Johnson. Contains numerous autobiographical stories, descriptions of contemporary life on the Onondaga Reservation, and descriptions of tribal customs, foods, history, and governmental. There are 54 texts altogether given in Onondaga only--13 told by Pat Johnson, 41 by Lucenda George. Of these texts, 35 are translated into English by Lucenda George as the earlier recordings are played back to her in short segments. There are no transcripts or other documentation accompanying these recordings.
22 open reel tapes (13 hr., 24 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, half track, mono; 7 in.
George, Lucenda
Johnson, Pat
Lukoff, Fred
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presented by Fred Lukoff in 1950. This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Note on Numbering
Tapes 16-22 were originally labeled as Tapes A-G. These tapes contains the translations of many of the recordings on tapes 1-15.
Related Recording
One wire spool from this collection was transferred to open reel tape in 1970 and can now be found in Mss.Rec.82.
Inheritance and succession; Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Onondaga Indians--Economic conditions; Onondaga Indians--Employment; Onondaga Indians--History; Onondaga Indians--Kinship; Onondaga Indians--Social conditions; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language; Sound recordings; Syracuse (N.Y.)
- Audio recordings
  - Text No. 1: Locusts, 1950-08-12; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:53; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Edible insects; Food habits; Locusts; Onondaga Indians--Food; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 2: Clifford's Garden this Summer, 1950-08-12; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:00; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Cucumbers; Gardening; Onondaga language; Summer; Weather
  - Text No. 3: Wintertime, 1950-08-12; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:49; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Automobile driving in winter; Onondaga language; Winter
  - Text No. 4: The Dam that was Built on the Reservation, 1950-08-12; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:42; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Dams--New York (State); Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Onondaga Indians--Land tenure; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 5: About the Funeral Yesterday, 1950-08-12; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:41; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Funeral rites and ceremonies; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 6: The Gypsies that are Now Camped on the Reservation, 1950-08-12; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:25; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Onondaga language; Romanies--New York (State)
  - Text No. 7: The Missionary Woman who is Boarding at Miss George's House, 1950-08-12; 01-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:32; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Edible insects; Food habits; Locusts; Missionaries; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 8: About Dorothy, 1950-08-12; 01-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:52; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indians--Social conditions; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language; Onondaga women
  - Text No. 9: About a Murder, 1950-08-12; 01-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:15; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Alcoholism; Murder; Onondaga Indians--Social conditions; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 10: About Running a Taxi, 1950-08-12; 01-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:24; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Indian women--Employment--United States; Indian women--North America--Social conditions; Onondaga Indians--Employment; Onondaga language; Taxicab drivers
  - Text No. 11: A Comparison of Olden Times and Present Times, 1950-08-12; 01; 02-11; 01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:59; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indians--Economic conditions; Onondaga Indians--Employment; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 12: The Hottest Summer and the Coldest Winter, 1950-08-12; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:37; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Cats; Onondaga language; Snow; Summer; Winter
  - Text No. 13: When Mrs. George Worked in a Gear Factory in Syracuse, 1950-08-12; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:39; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Factories--New York (State); Indian women--Employment--United States; Onondaga language; Syracuse (N.Y.); World War, 1914-1918--Participation, Indian
  - Text No. 14: Working in a Knitting Mill in Syracuse, 1950-08-12; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:55; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Indian women--Employment--United States; Onondaga Indians--Employment; Onondaga language; Syracuse (N.Y.); Textile workers
  - Text No. 15: Job Opportunities in Syracuse, 1950-08-12; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:25; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Agricultural laborers--New York (State); Onondaga Indians--Employment; Onondaga language; Syracuse (N.Y.)
  - Text No. 16: The Old House, 1950-08-12; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:07; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Moving of buildings, bridges, etc.; Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Onondaga language
  - Text No. 17: About an Onondaga Fellow and his Oneida Wife, 1950-08-12; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:54; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Evictions; Matriarchy; Oneida Indians; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 18: The Dead Feast or Reading of the Will, 1950-08-12; 02-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:21; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Matriarchy; Onondaga Indians--Legal status, laws, etc.; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language; Wills
  - Text No. 19: Onondaga Nation Property, 1950-08-12; 02-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:52; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indians--Government relations; Onondaga Indians--Land tenure; Onondaga Indians--Legal status, laws, etc.; Onondaga Indians--Social conditions; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 20: The Small Pox Epidemic on the Reservation, 1950-08-12; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:13; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Epidemics--New York (State); Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Onondaga Indians--History; Onondaga language; Smallpox
  - Text No. 21: Comparison of Indian Clothing of Today and Formerly, 1950-08-12; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:36; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indians--Clothing and dress; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 22: Falling in a Barrel of Water, 1950-08-12; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:15; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Autobiography; Children's accidents; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 23: The First Time I Rode a Horse, 1950-08-12; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:47; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Horsemanship; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 24: Something About Our Pets, 1950-08-12; 03-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:18; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Cats; Dogs; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language; Pets
  - Text No. 25: Onondaga Lake, 1950-08-13; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:55; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Scope and Contents note
    Original recording runs slightly fast.
    Onondaga Indians--Government relations; Onondaga Indians--History; Onondaga Indians--Land tenure; Onondaga Lake (N.Y.); Onondaga language
  - Text No. 26: Indian Foods, 1950-08-13; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:27; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Corn as food; Food habits; Onondaga Indians--Food; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 27: Pat's Autobiography, 1950-08-13; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:38; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indians--Biography; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 28: Sports, 1950-08-14; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:12; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language; Sports
  - Text No. 29: Christianity and the Longhouse Religion, 1950-08-14; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:02; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Christianity and other religions; Onondaga Indians--Religion; Onondaga Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 30: The Finger Lakes, 1950-08-14; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:27:27; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Finger Lakes (N.Y.); Onondaga Indians; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 31: About the Oneidas, 1950-08-14; 06-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:28; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Oneida Indians; Onondaga Indians; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 32: About Pat's Childhood, 1950-08-14; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:39; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Autobiography; Onondaga Indians--Biography; Onondaga Indians--History; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 33: An Experience at Cattaraugus, 1950-08; 08-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:58; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Autobiography; Cattaraugus Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Onondaga Indians--Biography; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 34: Snow Snakes, 1950-08; 09-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:46; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indians--Games; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 35: Pat's Job as a Messenger Boy, 1950-08; 09-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:09; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Autobiography; Messengers; Onondaga Indians--Biography; Onondaga Indians--Employment; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 36: Life on the Farm, 1950-08; 09-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:19:35; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Autobiography; Farms--New York (State); Onondaga Indians--Biography; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 37: Wampum and Brooches, 1950-08; 10-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:15; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Brooches; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language; Wampum
  - Text No. 38: Onondaga Inheritance Rules, 1950-08; 10-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:10; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Inheritance and succession; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 39: The Trips Pat has Taken, 1950-08; 11-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:28; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Autobiography; Onondaga Indians--Biography; Onondaga language; Voyages and travel
  - Text No. 40: The Time They Built the Road through the Reservation, 1950-08; 11-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:09; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Onondaga Indians--History; Onondaga language; Roads--Design and construction
  - Text No. 41: Talking About the Dead Feast for Tom Green, 1950-08; 12-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:47; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Fasts and feasts; Inheritance and succession; Onondaga Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Onondaga language; Wills
  - Text No. 42: Picnic at Owasco Lake, 1950-08; 12-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:11; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language; Owasco Lake (N.Y.); Picnicking
  - Text No. 43: The Watchman at the Dam, 1950-08; 12-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:14; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Assault and battery; Crime--Anecdotes; Missing persons; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 44: The Factions on the Reservation, 1950-08; 12-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:58; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Onondaga Indians--Politics and government; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 45: Lucenda's Trip Out West, 1950-08; 12-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:43; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indians--Biography; Onondaga language; Voyages and travel; West (U.S.)--Description and travel
  - Text No. 46: Family History, 1950-08; 13-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:04; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Inheritance and succession; Murder; Onondaga Indians--History--19th century; Onondaga language; Stepmothers
  - Text No. 47: About the Clans, 1950-08; 13-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:07; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Clans; Onondaga Indians--Kinship; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 48: Love Affairs, 1950-08; 13-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:21; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Diseases; Interracial marriage; Marriage; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 49: American Pension Club, 1950-08; 13-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:47; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indians--Economic conditions; Onondaga language; Pensions
  - Text No. 50: A Church Party, 1950-08; 14-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:20; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Churches; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Onondaga language; Parties
  - Text No. 51: An Old Lady Who Lost Her Money, 1950-08; 14-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:06; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Lost and found possessions; Money--Anecdotes; Older women; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 52: An Old Man Who Lost a Suit of Clothes, 1950-08; 14-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:48; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Clothing and dress; Lost and found possessions; Older men; Onondaga Indians; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 53: A Woman Who Lost Her Glasses, 1950-08; 14-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:57; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Glasses; Lost and found possessions; Onondaga Indians; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 54: About the Six Nations, 1950-08; 15-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:00; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indians; Onondaga language; Six Nations
  - Text No. 1: Locusts, 1950-08; 16-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:59; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    A translation into English of a recorded Onondaga text as it is played back to the speaker in segments.
  - Text No. 2: Clifford's Garden this Summer, 1950-08; 16-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:25; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 3: Wintertime, 1950-08; 16-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:41; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 4: The Dam that was Built on the Reservation, 1950-08; 16-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:05; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 5: About the Funeral Yesterday, 1950-08; 16-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:06; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 6: The Gypsies that are Now Camped on the Reservation, 1950-08; 16-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:11; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 7: The Missionary Woman who is Boarding at Miss George's House, 1950-08; 16-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:46; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 8: About Dorothy, 1950-08; 16-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:16; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 9: About a Murder, 1950-08; 16-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:57; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 10: About Running a Taxi, 1950-08; 16-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:23; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 11: A Comparison of Olden Times and Present Times, 1950-08; 17-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:07; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 12: The Hottest Summer and the Coldest Winter, 1950-08; 17-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:09; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 13: When Mrs. George Worked in a Gear Factory in Syracuse, 1950-08; 17-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:40; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Factories--New York (State); Indian women--Employment--United States; Onondaga Indians--Employment; Syracuse (N.Y.); World War, 1914-1918--Participation, Indian
  - Text No. 14: Working in a Knitting Mill in Syracuse, 1950-08; 17-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:34; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 15: Job Opportunities in Syracuse, 1950-08; 17-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:55; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 16: The Old House, 1950-08; 17-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:58; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 17: About an Onondaga Fellow and his Oneida Wife, 1950-08; 17-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:31; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 18: The Dead Feast or Reading of the Will, 1950-08; 17-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:53; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Inheritance and succession; Matriarchy; Onondaga Indians--Legal status, laws, etc.; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Wills
  - Text No. 19: Onondaga Nation Property, 1950-08; 17-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:02; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Onondaga Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Onondaga Indians--Government relations; Onondaga Indians--Land tenure; Onondaga Indians--Legal status, laws, etc.; Onondaga Indians--Social conditions
  - Text No. 20: The Small Pox Epidemic on the Reservation, 1950-08; 18-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:19:37; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 21: Comparison of Indian Clothing of Today and Formerly, 1950-08; 18-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:57; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 22: Falling in a Barrel of Water, 1950-08; 18-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:14; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Children's accidents; Onondaga language
  - Text No. 23: The First Time I Rode a Horse, 1950-08; 18-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:16; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 24: Something About Our Pets, 1950-08; 18-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:53; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    Cats; Dogs; Onondaga Indians--Domestic animals; Onondaga Indians--Social life and customs; Pets
  - Text No. 41: Talking About the Dead Feast for Tom Green, 1950-08; 19-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:18; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
    A translation into English of a recorded Onondaga text as it is played back to the speaker in segments. Recording begins in English only, with the Tuscarora recording skipped, but is included later on.
  - Text No. 42: Picnic at Owasco Lake, 1950-08; 19-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:13; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 43: The Watchman at the Dam, 1950-08; 19-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:34; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 46: Family History, 1950-08; 20-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:23; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 47: About the Clans, 1950-08; 20-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:05; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 48: Love Affairs, 1950-08; 20-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:19:55; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 49: American Pension Club, 1950-08; 20-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:32; George, Lucenda; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 37: Wampum and Brooches, 1950-08; 21-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:27:07; George, Lucenda; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 38: Onondaga Inheritance Rules, 1950-08; 21-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:37:40; George, Lucenda; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 25: Onondaga Lake, 1950-08; 22-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:24:00; George, Lucenda; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
  - Text No. 26: Indian Foods, 1950-08; 22-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:46; George, Lucenda; Johnson, Pat; Lukoff, Fred
    A translation into English of a recorded Onondaga text as it is played back to the speaker in segments. Program ends before the completion of translation of the original recorded text.